<sect1 id="status-pages">
<title>Translation status pages</title>

<sect2>
<title>Introduction
</title>

<para>
The &d-i; team and the &i18n-coords; maintain web pages giving the
statistics of translations for each language, level by level. The
scripts that generate these statistics may be found in the
<filename>scripts/l10n/statistics</filename> directory of &d-i;
<acronym>SVN</acronym> repository.
</para>

<para>
Translators should check these pages regularly in order to follow the
possible changes to upstream packages and then update their work if
needed.
</para>

<para>The address for the top page of translation statistics is <ulink
url="&url-d-i-translation-status;">&url-d-i-translation-status;</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
The statistics page will give statistics about translations as close
as possible from the sources. If the package maintainer for a given
package uses a publicly accessible repository, the statistics are
generated from this repository.
</para>

<para>
The real status for each package (i.e. the status of translations for
the packages released in the Debian archive) can be found on the
Debian general l10n pages: <ulink
url="&url-debian-l10n;">&url-debian-l10n;</ulink>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Status pages generation scripts
</title>

<para>
FIXME: Here should come details about the status pages generation scripts: how the script work, how are determined packages and how information about packages locations is kept, status pages template file, etc.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Status pages monitoring
</title>

<para>
Translators often want an easy method for watching the translation
status pages and learn about changes in packages listed in the various
<emphasis>levels</emphasis> there.
</para>

<para>
For this, Peter Mann wrote a monitoring script named <classname>websec-txt</classname>. This script is available in the <classname>scripts/l10n</classname> directory in &d-i; SVN repository.
</para>

<para>
Using this script is fairly easy. It requires the use of a Unix system
with wget and a working Internet connection. One should then create a
directory such as <classname>$HOME/.websec-txt</classname> and put a
file named <classname>sources.url</classname> there. This file should
contain the contents of the monitored files.
</para>

<para>
Below is the suggested contents for monitoring &d-i; translation status pages (assuming &lt;code&gt; being the translators language ISO-639 code):</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
&url-status;/level1/&lt;code&gt;.txt
&url-status;/level2/&lt;code&gt;.txt
&url-status;/level3/&lt;code&gt;.txt
&url-status;/level4/&lt;code&gt;.txt
&url-status;/level5/&lt;code&gt;.txt
</screen>
</informalexample>

</sect2>

</sect1>

