<appendix id="bug-reports"><title>Reporting bugs against Debian packages</title>

<para>
This section applies to translators who need to send their completed
translations back to the package maintainers, especially for packages
from levels above 2 for which no direct Subversion commit is
possible (either because the translator cannot use <acronym>GIT</acronym> or
because the package maintainer(s) do not encourage wide commit
access).
</para>

<sect1>
<title>
Debian bug reports, severities and tags
</title>

<para>
All interactions with Debian package maintainers should be made through the
Debian Bug Tracking System (BTS). Other ways of interaction such as sending
files to maintainers directly, or to the &i18n-coords; is to be prohibited as
it makes things impossible to track down.
</para>

<para>
The &i18n-coords; will not encourage direct interaction with either
them or the package maintainers. The only exception are cases where
translators have direct commit access to the package repositories such
as &d-i; level 1 translations.
</para>

<para>
A <emphasis>bug report</emphasis> is only a special way to send
traceable information which is relevant for a given package. This may
be a <quote>real</quote> bug report (i.e. something not working properly or as
expected) as well as an enhancement suggestion or a feature request.
</para>

<para>
Debian bug reports are handled through a web and e-mail
interface. Access to the bug reports can be made through the BTS web
site: &url-bts;.
</para>

<para>
Bug reports are sorted by <emphasis>severity</emphasis> and
<emphasis>tags</emphasis>.
</para>

<para>
Details about bug severities, tags and other information regarding bug
reports may be found at <ulink url="&url-bts;">&url-bts;</ulink>.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Recommended bug formatting for translation bug reports
</title>

<para>
For translation bug reports, the recommended severity to use is
<emphasis>wishlist</emphasis>. 
</para>

<para>
The recommended tags are <emphasis>l10n</emphasis> tag as well as the
<emphasis>patch</emphasis> tag (because the bug report includes the
needed "fix" by including the translation file).
</para>

<para>
The <emphasis>d-i</emphasis> tag must be used for core D-I
translations as well as base-config and tasksel.
</para>

<para>
The subject of the bug report should start with "[INTL:xx]". When the
package has several translatable materials, the subject should mention
which translation is sent.
</para>

<para>
When translators want to send more than one translation file, they
should send one bug report per file to send, in order to avoid
confusion. The bug report must mention which type of translation is
sent (debconf, programs, etc.).
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Generic method to send bug reports
</title>

<para>
Reporting a bug to a Debian package is just a matter of sending a specially
formatted mail to &email-bts;.
</para>

<para>
The mail should include <emphasis>in the mail body</emphasis>, at the
top, a few special pseudo-fields:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
Package: &lt;package name&gt;
Version: &lt;version of the package&gt;
Severity: &lt;bug severity&gt;
Tags: &lt;bug tags&gt;
</screen>
</informalexample>


<para>
As a consequence, the following is a typical manual bug report
(Klingon translation for the shadow package sent by the translator
named John Doe):
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
From: John Doe &lt;john.doe@johndoe.com&gt;
To: &email-bts;
Subject: [INTL:tlh] Klingon debconf templates translation

Package: shadow
Version: N/A
Severity: wishlist
Tags: l10n patch

Please find attached the Klingon translation of the shadow package.

(encoded tlh.po file follows)
</screen>
</informalexample>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Sending bug reports from a Debian system
</title>

<para>
Translators are encouraged to use the Debian
<command>reportbug</command> utility which will handle all these
formatting details for them.
</para>

<para>
An example command line follows. It will report a bug against the
<emphasis>shadow</emphasis> package with the Klingon (code: tlh) translation:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
reportbug --attach=tlh.po --offline \
  -s "shadow: [INTL:tlh] Klingon debconf templates translation" \
  --severity=wishlist --tag=patch --tag=l10n --no-config-files \
  shadow
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
The <command>reportbug</command> utility must be configured for using
correct originating address and real name. See <command>man
reportbug</command> for details. An example ~/.reportbugrc is given
below. Do not use it directly but adapt it to your own needs!
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
# reportbug preferences file
# Version of reportbug this preferences file was written by
reportbug_version "1.99.51"
# default operating mode: one of: novice, standard, advanced, expert
mode standard
# default user interface
ui text
# offline setting - comment out to be online
#offline
# name and e-mail setting (if non-default)
realname "John Doe"
email "johndoe@johndoe.com"
# You can add other settings after this line.  See
# /etc/reportbug.conf for a full listing of options.
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
It is also worth mentioning the <command>reportbug-ng</command>
package which features a user-friendly bug reporting utility with full
desktop integration.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Attaching files to bug reports
</title>

<para>
Translation bug reports usually need a file to be attached to the bug report.
</para>

<para>
To avoid encoding problems, especially on package maintainers side,
compressing the translation file with <command>gzip</command> is
recommended.
</para>

</sect1>

</appendix>
