<appendix id="gettext-tools"><title>Gettext files editors and tools</title>

<sect1>
<title>
Gettext files editors
</title>

<para>
Translators are highly encouraged to use dedicated GNU gettext message
catalogs files (PO files) editing tools. Even though PO files are
plain text files which may be modified with any text editor, the use
of dedicated tools will save translators a lot of time.
</para>

<para>
This document does not intend to be a reference document about these
tools. Most tools have been packaged for the Debian GNU/Linux
distribution and thus installing them on a Debian system is as easy as
running <command>apt install &lt;package&gt;</command>.
</para>

<para>Short list of PO editing tools:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Lokalize</emphasis> (Debian package
      <classname>lokalize</classname>): very complete and
      powerful. Needs installing the KDE libraries (but, of course, it
      may work without the full KDE environment).
    </para>
    <para>
      The Lokalize editor (formerly KBabel) is undoubtfully the most complete gettext
      message catalogs editor and its use is recommended by the
      &i18n-coords;. Its support for non-Latin languages is very
      complete, including correct Right-To-Left (RTL) and BiDi support
      for Arabic/Hebrew and other RTL languages as well as support for
      combined languages such as languages using the Devanagari script.
    </para>
    <para>
      The major drawback is for Gnome users: it may be quite long
      to launch and memory hungry because of the need of KDE and Qt
      libraries.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Gtranslator</emphasis> (Debian package
      <classname>gtranslator</classname>): PO-file editor for the
      GNOME Desktop.
    </para>
    <para>
      Gtranslator is roughly the equivalent of Lokalize for users of the
      Gnome environment. Of course, it can be used outside the Gnome
      environment with the same drawback as Lokalize.
    </para>
    <para>
      However, it is not well suited for &d-i; translations as
      <emphasis>it does not properly support Plural
      Forms</emphasis>. So translators working on files which include
      plural forms (<classname>base-config</classname> are among those
      files) should absolutely avoid using Gtranslator.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Poedit</emphasis> (Debian package
      <classname>poedit</classname>): quite complete tool but no
      correct handling of non Latin languages on Debian. Uses the
      WxWindows toolkit.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Emacs <emphasis>po-mode</emphasis> (Debian package
      <classname>gettext-el</classname>): editing mode for the
      Emacs/XEmacs editor. Emacs wizards will probably appreciate
      using the same editing environment for gettext message catalog
      files.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Emacs po-mode is however limited when it comes to "advanced"
      features such as auto-learning, message compendiums use and
      other very useful features for translators.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>


</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Gettext files tools
</title>

<para>
The Debian package <emphasis>gettext</emphasis> includes a whole set of command-line
utilities for handling i18n material.
</para>

<para>Several utilities may help translators in manipulating the PO files
contents. For all these utilities, see their respective man pages for
details about their use:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>msgcat</command> combines together one or several
      files. When used on a single file, it will wrap the file
      contents and make it easy to read.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>msgmerge</command> may merge together translations from
      one or two files as well as update a PO files according to the
      contents of a <filename>templates</filename> file.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>msgfmt</command> is aimed at compiling message catalog
      files but is also very useful for checking files and get
      statistics about their contents. The use of <command>msgfmt
      --check --statistics --output-file=/dev/null
      &language;.po</command> is highly recommended before commiting a
      translation file or sending it to the package maintainer.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Debian specific tools
</title>

<para>
<command>podebconf-display-po</command> will give translators a rough
idea on how their translation will look like, particularly the screens
length (use this utility on a usual 80x25 terminal).  But as cdebconf
and debconf displays slightly differ, and as some scripts do heavy use
of text substitution, one should not fully rely on this program. Running
debian-installer is the only reliable solution to test your translation.
(Note: this does not work for the po files from level 1 under
<emphasis>sublevelX</emphasis>!)
</para>

<para>
Using <command>podebconf-display-po</command> is mandatory for testing
debconf translations when they are mentioned to be tricky (such as
<classname>shadow</classname>,
<classname>popularity-contest</classname> and exim4 translations).
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Spellchecking tools
</title>

<para>
<classname>aspell</classname>: this package is designed for testing
the spelling in PO files as it will only test the spelling in their
translated part. It relies on the <command>ispell</command> program :
this will then only work with languages for which an ispell dictionary
exists.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Gettext files headers
</title>

<para>
Translators should not forget to properly fill up the PO files header,
especially the <userinput>Last-Translator</userinput> field.
</para>

<para>
The <userinput>Project-Id-Version</userinput> field should be filled
with the package name : this will help translators in translation maintenance.
</para>


</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Plural Forms
</title>

<para>
Foo
</para>

</sect1>




</appendix>
