<appendix id="svn-basics"><title>Some basic notions about <acronym>SVN</acronym>/<acronym>git</acronym></title>

<sect1>
<title>Getting an account on &alioth;
</title>

<para>
<acronym>SVN</acronym>/<acronym>git</acronym> commit access requires the creation of an account on the &alioth;
server. This is as simple as opening &url-alioth; and going to the
account creation pages.
</para>

<para>
Official Debian developers will probably use the same login as their
Debian login, but must go through the account creation process
anyway. Non-Debian developers should be aware that the login they
will choose on &alioth; will be followed by <quote>-guest</quote>. This has
absolutely no meaning of any kind of <emphasis>second class
citizens</emphasis> but is just an easy way for &alioth; system
administrators to know who is an official Debian developer.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Installing <acronym>SVN</acronym> and <acronym>git</acronym>/<acronym>myrepos</acronym>
</title>

<para>
Translators need to install <acronym>SVN</acronym>
(Subversion) on their system. Just do <command>apt-get install
subversion</command>
</para>

<para>
&d-i; contributors who want to work on the code of the installer (so not just translation
work), additionally need to install <acronym>git</acronym> and <acronym>myrepos</acronym>
by <command>apt-get install git myrepos</command>
</para>

<para>
Users of non-Debian Linux distributions will probably easily find
installation sources for Subversion and git in their distribution packages
list.
</para>

<para>
For MS-Windows users, a good <acronym>SVN</acronym> client is <emphasis>TortoiseSVN</emphasis>, which is free software. It can be downloaded from <ulink url="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/">http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
Successful attempts of using <emphasis>TortoiseSVN</emphasis> for &d-i; commits have been reported. The only trick is to feed the checkout URL alone to the "svn import" command of <emphasis>TortoiseSVN</emphasis>, without the leading "svn co" part.
</para>


</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Using <acronym>SVN</acronym>/<acronym>git</acronym> to get and commit files
</title>

<para>
Once their account is allowed to write to the project, translators
can download the translation files using the
checkout commands mentioned in <xref linkend="translators"/>.
</para>

<para>
Developers can download the full project source tree using
svn and git checkout commands as detailed in <xref linkend="maintainers"/>.
Note, that this is not necessary for translators!
</para>

<para>
For doing <filename>svn+ssh</filename> connections (mandatory for
being able to commit files later), users must have an account on
&alioth; and be authorized for commit to the repository they want to
checkout. Replace <emphasis>alioth_username</emphasis> by this login
name before using the SVN pseudo-URLS.
</para>

<para>
<filename>svn+ssh</filename> connections require you to use RSA key-based authentication to connect to &alioth;.
</para>

<para>
If you don't have an existing SSH keypair on your local system, you must create one with the <command>ssh-keygen</command> command.
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
spongebob@mykerinos:~$ ssh-keygen -t rsa
Generating public/private rsa key pair.
Enter file in which to save the key (/home/spongebob/.ssh/id_dsa):
Enter passphrase (empty for no passphrase):
Enter same passphrase again:
Your identification has been saved in /home/spongebob/.ssh/id_rsa.
Your public key has been saved in /home/spongebob/.ssh/id_rsa.pub.
The key fingerprint is:
8d:6d:14:72:72:07:01:6a:85:de:97:d3:aa:b2:ee:4a spongebob@mykerinos
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
In the example below, the user <emphasis>spongebob</emphasis> creates a SSH RSA keypair, which is saved in a directory named <filename>.ssh</filename> in his/her home directory.
</para>

<para>
This keypair is protected by a passphrase. The passphrase has to be entered each time the keypair will be used to connect to a remote host. Take care to choose a non trivial passphrase.
</para>

<para>
After doing so, the public part of that keypair must be put in your account on &alioth;. For this, you need to output the contents of <filename>.ssh/id_rsa.pub</filename> and paste it in the relevant field of the account management page on &alioth; (&alioth-account-page;), in the section named <emphasis>Shell account informations</emphasis>, by clicking on <emphasis>Edit keys</emphasis>.
</para>


<para>
In case users have problems with <acronym>SVN</acronym> checkouts/commits, they can ask
for help, either on IRC, &irc-channel; or by mail with the
&i18n-coords;.</para>

<para>
MS-Windows users who want to use TortoiseSVN to checkout or commit can go to the <ulink url="http://tortoisesvn.net/node/5">TortoiseSVN SSH HowTo</ulink> page to get information about setting up TortoiseSVN to do SVN+SSH connections.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Testing <acronym>SVN</acronym> commit access to &d-i; repository
</title>

<para>
A <emphasis>sandbox</emphasis> directory has been setup for developers
and translators to practice with <acronym>SVN</acronym> before doing
real work.
</para>

The sequence for testing commit access should be similar to what
follows. Please note that, depending whether your SSH keys have been
added to your account on &svn-debian;, you can be prompted for a
password up to three times. This is because of the special
authentication setup on &svn-debian;.

<informalexample>
<screen>
cd &lt;somedir&gt;
svn co &svn-di-sandbox;
Password:
Password:
Password:
.../... (checkout should happen here)

cd sandbox
echo "Testcommit" >foo
svn add foo
svn ci -m "Testcommit of a file" foo
.../...
svn remove foo
svn ci -m "Remove the test file"
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
As stated by the <filename>README.txt</filename> file in this
directory, please avoid commiting large files for testing as this
clutters up the SVN server history.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Core &d-i; and various levels packages repositories checkout command
lines
</title>

<para>
Typical non anonymous and anonymous checkout command lines for &d-i;
and related packages are listed in <xref linkend="translators"/>.
</para>

<para>
Below is an example of a typical checkout for the console-data package:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
user@host:~> &svn-console-data;
TODO
user@host:~> 
</screen>
<para>
After this the <filename>console-data</filename> directory contains all
files from the package. Updating this directory later needs running the <command>svn update</command>:
</para>
<screen>
user@host:~> cd console-data
user@host:~/console-data> svn up
TODO
user@host:~>
</screen>
<para>
Subdirectories of a full <acronym>SVN</acronym> directory can also be checked out in case one want to work on specific parts. This can be very useful for &d-i; core translations as &d-i; <acronym>SVN</acronym> repository is very big:
</para>
<screen>
user@host:~> &svn-level1; level1-po
TODO
user@host:~> cd level1-po/
user@host:~/level1-po> ls -l
total 19112
-rw-r--r--  1 user user 369598 2005-08-18 02:56 ar.po
-rw-r--r--  1 user user 266462 2005-08-18 02:56 be.po
.../...
-rw-r--r--  1 user user   1120 2005-07-17 08:17 PROSPECTIVE
.../...
-rw-r--r--  1 user user   2027 2005-07-31 08:54 README
-rw-r--r--  1 user user 353752 2005-08-18 02:56 ro.po
-rw-r--r--  1 user user    324 2005-08-16 16:30 run-l10n-sync
.../...
-rw-r--r--  1 user user 237996 2005-08-18 02:56 template.pot
.../...
-rw-r--r--  1 user user 350181 2005-08-18 02:56 xh.po
-rw-r--r--  1 user user 335898 2005-08-18 02:56 zh_CN.po
-rw-r--r--  1 user user 335413 2005-08-18 02:56 zh_TW.po
user@host:~/level1-po>
</screen>
<para>
If the translation file already exists, then just update the local copy:
</para>
<screen>
user@host:~/level1-po> lokalize fr.po
.../...
</screen>
<para>
(Use Lokalize or any other gettext utility, see <xref linkend="gettext-tools"/> for details about gettext files handling, editing and maintenance tools.)
</para>
<para>
Once you have saved the modified version of the file, the status can be
displayed with the <command>svn status</command> command:
</para>
<screen>
user@host:~/level1-po> svn status
M      fr.po
user@host:~/level1-po>
</screen>
<para>
The above means that <filename>fr.po</filename> includes uncommited
modifications. These modifications can be committed by using the <command>svn commit</command> command:
</para>
<screen>
user@host:~/level1-po> svn commit
</screen>
<para>
The user will then be dropped into a file editor (either
<command>vi</command> or any other file editor pointed by the EDITOR
variable. The changelog message can then be typed in the
editor. Saving it and exiting the editor will trigger the commit
action to the <acronym>SVN</acronym> repository.
</para>
<para>
A more targeted commit command is also possible, as well as giving the
commit message on the command line:
</para>
<screen>
user@host:~/level1-po> svn commit -m"French translation update" fr.po
TODO
user@host:~/level1-po>
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
In general, a few recommendations can be made to translators:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Always use the <command>svn update</command> before working on a
file or directory. This will minimize <emphasis>conflicts</emphasis>
in case a file is changed in the repository while they work on it;
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Always use the <command>svn status</command> command before committing
changes, to be sure that only relevant changes are committed.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Changelog entries handling
</title>
<para>
When committing translations directly to <acronym>SVN</acronym>
repositories for Debian packages (except for level 1 translations),
translators must update the <filename>debian/changelog</filename> file
accordingly.
</para>

<para>
This <emphasis>does not</emphasis> apply to level 1 translations, that
is the &d-i; <emphasis>core</emphasis> packages translations. For
these translations, no changelog updates are needed.
</para>

<para>
Each change in Debian packages must be documented in the
<filename>debian/changelog</filename> file.
</para>

<para>
Below is an excerpt of the <filename>changelog</filename> file for
&base-config;:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
base-config (2.39) UNRELEASED; urgency=low

  * Updated translations: 
    - Croatian by Krunoslav Gernhard

 -- Christian Perrier &lt;bubulle@debian.org&gt;  Sat, 24 Jul 2004 08:14:13 +0200

base-config (2.38) unstable; urgency=high
.../...
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>This gives the following information:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
the last released version of the package is 2.38. The <acronym>SVN</acronym> repository
  currently contains the future unpublished 2.39 release;
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
the only change which occurred since 2.38 is the update of the Croatian
  translation (made by Krunoslav Gernhard);
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
the committer of this change was Christian Perrier.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Different Debian packages may use slightly different methods and
styles for <filename>changelog</filename> maintenance. When working
with <acronym>SVN</acronym>/<acronym>CVS</acronym> repositories, using <emphasis>UNRELEASED</emphasis> for the last entry is highly recommended for new unpublished changes.
</para>

<para>
Using the <command>debchange</command> utility from the
<emphasis>devscripts</emphasis> Debian package for handling
<filename>changelog</filename> entries maintenance is also highly
recommended..
</para>


</sect1>


</appendix>
