<sect1 id="active">
<title>
Active languages
</title>

<para>
Active languages are languages which are not listed in the prospective languages
list. If languages are removed from this list, the synchronisation script will
then start to sync those translations with the indvidual &d-i; packages (see
<xref linkend="synchronisation-scripts"/>).
</para>

<para>
This section describes the technical operations that should take place when
the decision to activate a given language is taken by the &i18n-coords;.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>
Removing the language from the prospective list
</title>

<para>
The first action to take place is the removal of the language from the
<filename>packages/po/PROSPECTIVE</filename> file.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Run the synchronization script
</title>

<para>
The synchronization script should then be run so that new translations are
spread out to D-I packages. Of course, these translations will only be
available in the D-I images, when new versions of these packages are uploaded.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Activate language in localechooser
</title>

<para>
The language should be activated in the <classname>localechooser</classname>
package. For this, the language entry in the <filename>languagelist</filename>
should be uncommented and the  <classname>localechooser</classname> must be
rebuilt and uploaded.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Uploading D-I packages
</title>

<para>
For the translation to be effective, all &d-i; packages with localized messages
should be rebuilt and uploaded. Until this happens, translations for that language
will not appear.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Add or check tasks in tasksel
</title>

<para>
Tasks related to the new language should be considered for addition in tasksel
(see <xref linkend="language-tasks"/>).
</para>

<para>
These tasks should also be added in the <filename>tasks.list</filename> file of
the <classname>debian-cd</classname> package, so that CD or DVD prioritize the task's
components for inclusion on first CDs or DVDs.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Check the availability of font for the graphical installer
</title>

<para>
A check should be made for the chosen font for the graphical installer. In case a
dedicated font is needed, the udeb providing that font must be existing, or a patch
should be created against the relevant package for it to provide this udeb package.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Record the new status of the language
</title>

<para>
The status of the relevant language chould be changed in
<filename>installer/doc/i18n/languages.xml</filename>. "prospective" should be
removed from the "nlp_step" field and the "supported" field should be changed from
<quote>false</quote> to the next version of the installer release (see other languages
for examples).
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Add language to utility script
</title>

<para>
The language should be added
in <filename>scripts/l10n/output-l10n-changes</filename> list of languages.
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

